Herrera, Leonel; Collection apap300
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Leonel Herrera Collection
1954-2007
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Herrera, Leonel, 1947-1993
Ellis, Norma Herrera, 1954-2008
apap300
1.27 cubic ft.
The Herrera Collection contain materials associated with the life and trial of Leonel Herrera, as well as materials included in the book Last Words from Death Row: The Walls Unit, written by Leonel Herrera’s sister, Norma Herrera Ellis.
Collection X
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this collection were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in 2007 by Norma Herrera Ellis.
Historical Note
Leonel Herrera was born September 17, 1947. He was the second of five children born to parents Jose and Maria Herrera in McAllen, Texas. He attended local schools from 1954-1963, and then in 1967 enlisted in the Armed Forces of the United States until given an Undesirable Discharge in 1969.
Leonel Herrera was arrested in 1981 and sentenced to die for the shooting to death of Enrique Carrisalez, a police officer who stopped him for speeding in the Rio Grande Valley. Leonel Herrera petitioned against the death penalty, eventually claiming to have additional evidence that proved his innocence and proved that his late brother, Raul Herrera, committed the murder. The additional evidence was not accepted by Texas judges, who argued that regardless of what new evidence might be presented, Herrera was given a fair trial and therefore the jury’s decision could not be overturned. Herrera's advocates claimed that keeping Herrera on death row, despite evidence that might prove his innocence, was a form of cruel and unusual punishment and therefore a violation of the Eighth Amendment. The case ultimately went to the Supreme Court of the United States which denied Herrera’s appeal in the 1993 decision Herrera v. Collins. The Supreme Court ruled that a claim of innocence does not entitle a petitioner to habeas corpus relief by way of the Eighth or Fourteenth Amendments. The State of Texas executed Leonel Herrera on May 12, 1993 at 4:49 a.m.
A retired nurse, Norma Herrera Ellis (1954-2008), Leonel Herrera’s sister, published Last Words from Death Row: The Walls Unit in 2007. Last Words from Death Row: The Walls Unit is a biography following Leonel Herrera’s trial and press coverage. Norma Herrera Ellis wrote Last Words as part of a promise to tell her brother’s story. She continued to advocate for his innocence until her death on January 14, 2008, at age 54.
Scope and Contents
The Leonel Herrera Collection contains research materials on the death penalty in the United States with a focus on the right of the convicted to submit evidence of their innocence to delay their own execution.
The collection, donated by Leonel Herrera's sister Norma Herrera Ellis, includes photographs, court documents, news clippings, official and personal correspondence, VHS tapes, and religious memorabilia either owned by or involving Leonel Herrera. Additional materials are included because of their usage in Norma Herrera Ellis' book Last Words from Death Row: The Walls Unit. Many newspaper clippings refer to the drug cartel the Herrera family and local police were involved in. Other newspaper clippings discuss the Leonel Herrera Case with a focus on opinion pieces about later courts refusing Herrera’s additional evidence to demonstrate his innocence. Photographs are mixed family photos, postcards, and rally photos, with the bulk being family photos.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized chronologically. There are no series.
Separated Materials
The archivist transferred one monograph: Last Words from Death Row: The Walls Unit by Norma Herrera Ellis to the book division of Special Collections. It will be catalogued and included in Minerva, the University Libraries Catalog.
Capital punishment--Texas; Herrera, Leonel, 1947-1993; Correspondence.; Photographs.; Clippings; Legal documents; Death Penalty
- Leonel Herrera Report Cards, Elementary to High School, 1954-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Photos and Postcards, Leonel Herrera and Family, After 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Military Service Records of Leonel Herrera, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Notice of Overpayment to IRS by Leonel Herrera, 1970 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Raul Herrera Judgement, 1973 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Food Establishment Permit Issued to Leonel Herrera, 1976 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Original Indictment, Leonel Herrera, 1981 October 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Precept to Serve, 1981 December 29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Judgement of Conviction, Incomplete, 1982 January 21 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1982; 1989-1990; 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Craft Arts and Cards Created by Leonel Herrera, 1982-1983; 1987; 1990; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Legal Correspondence Regarding Leonel Herrera Case, 1982-1985; 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Injury Report and Solitary Confinement Physical Examination, 1983 June (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Affidavits, Leonel Herrera Case, 1983-1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Inmate Files, Leonel Herrera, 1983; 1985; 1993; 2002 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Polygraph Reports, Leonel Herrera Case, 1983; 1993; Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Ex Parte Motion for Compensation, 1990 December 12 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Petition for Writ of Habeas Corpus, Appendix (1 of 2), 1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Petition for Writ of Habeas Corpus, Appendix (2 of 2), 1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Judge Clinton Response to Habeas Corpus Application, 1991 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Habeas Corpus Application Response, 1991 August 07 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Amended Order on Application for Writ of Habeas Corpus, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Correspondence to Leonel Herrera, 1991; 1993 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Open Letter by Robert McGlasson, 1992 February 19 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- National Public Radio Transcript, 1992 October 07 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Newspaper Clippings, Kept by Leonel Herrera, 1992 May (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Petition for Writ of Habeas Corpus, Appendix (Box 2, Folder 4)
- CBS Evening News "Leo: Eye on America", ca. 1992 (Video-tape 1)
- Petition for Stay of Execution, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- CBS Evening News "Eye on America" Transcript, 1992; 1995 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Leonel Herrera and Gary Graham Rally Memo, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Petition for Writ of Habeas Corpus, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Request to the Governor for Ninety Day Reprieve of Death Sentence, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Leonel Herrera Funeral Pamphlets, ca. 1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Personal Correspondence to Norma Herrera, 1993-1995; 1997; 2002 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Herrera Family Album, Undated (Oversized 1)
- Herrera Family Album (1 of 2), Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Herrera Family Album (2 of 2), Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Newspaper Clippings, Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Photos of Anti-Execution Rally, Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Photos of Leonel Herrera Grave, Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Religious Memorabilia Owned by Leonel Herrera, Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Video Made for Leo's Appeal, Undated (Video-tape 2)